number four asks which of the marked
loan pairs on the following compound is
delocalized so what this is asking is is
there any loone pair on here such that
we could draw another resonance
structure by turning that loone pair
into a calent bond pushing some other P
electron density onto some other portion
of the molecule which one of these lone
pairs can be moved around essentially so
let's look at number one first we have
an oxygen we have two lone pairs there
is there anywhere that these can go can
we for example take this lone pair and
put it right there well we can't here
because this carbon already has four
bonds it's got a bond to oxygen two
bonds to these two carbon atoms there's
an implied hydrogen it is not going to
be able to accommodate any other bonds
we need access to other Pi electrons
that can Shuffle around in some other
way we have a pi Bond over here but
that's just too far away it's not going
to be able to interact with this one so
that's going to be no let's look at
number two we have a lone pair here is
it the case that this can go down here
well in this case it actually can
because this is adjacent to this Pi bond
this CN Sigma bond is adjacent to this
CC double bond which has a sigma and a
pi Bond so if we push this loan paired
down like that we can also take this Pi
Bond and push it right there and we
could put the anion on that carbon
instead we would end up with n plus and
C minus this is the case that this loone
pair is delocalized that is going to be
number two let's just look at the other
options with the Florine atom we've got
three lone pairs here is it the case
that we can take a lone pair and push it
there well no we can't because again
we've got a carbon atom here that's got
four bonds already it's not going to be
able to accommodate another Bond because
it cannot lose a bond the way that this
carbon atom did right this carbon atom
was able to accommodate a new Bond
because it was able to lose a bond as
well and remain coordinated with four
bonds there so this one can't do it
that's no good and then the same thing
here with oxygen this just isn't going
to work this oxygen could take one of
these piie bonds but we're not going to
form yet another Bond here because this
carbon has no bond that it can lose so
this also is not going to work again in
order for the lone pair to be
delocalized we have to be able to draw
another resonance structure like we did
here where this loone pair goes down we
form a pi Bond there and then we lose
that piie bond that flies up and gives
you the Ion on the carbon atom so that
one is going to be B lone pair number
two